Guide to the David Birnbach New York State Dept. of Mental Hygiene Oral History records, 1983-2002.
Birnbach, David New York State Dept. of Mental Hygiene Oral History records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
David Birnbach New York State Dept. of Mental Hygiene Oral History records, 1983-2002.
6821
Birnbach
3.2 cubic feet.
Audio tapes, correspondence, transcripts
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Audio recordings and transcriptions of interviews David Birnbach conducted with former staff of New York State mental hospitals.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
David Birnbach worked at New York State's Suffolk Developmental Center from 1977-1979 and at Willard Psychiatric Center from 1979-1983.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Audio recordings and transcriptions of interviews David Birnbach conducted with former staff of New York State mental hospitals including Willard, Gowanda, St. Lawrence, Rochester, Sunmount, Pilgrim, and Rockland in 1983 and 1984. The interviews from Gowanda were the most comprehensive. Also particularly important are interviews from St. Lawrence, the first state hospital in the nation to open all its locked wards, and Rochester with its focus on leadership and integration in an urban setting. Also included are research materials on the subject and a draft of Birnbach's research results finished in 2002 and titled "Before, during, and shortly after the custody, care and treatment revolution: An oral history of the New York State Department of Mental Hygiene, 1928-1983."
SUBJECTS
Names:
Birnbach, David.; Gowanda Psychiatric Center (N.Y.); New York (State). Dept. of Mental Hygiene.; Rochester Psychiatric Center (N.Y.); St. Lawrence Psychiatric Center (Ogdensburg, N.Y.); Willard Psychiatric Center (N.Y.); Willard State Hospital (N.Y.)
Subjects:
Mental retardation facilities -- New York (State).; Psychiatric hospitals -- New York (State) -- History.
Form and Genre Terms:
Audiocassettes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
This collection may only be used for consultation. No reproductions can be made without permission of the archivist. No publication of information within this collection can be made without permission of the archivist. Use of names from this collection anywhere may only be done with permission of the archivist. A name index of the interviewees is available offline. Researchers may request confirmation of inclusion of individuals in the collection by name. The complete list of names can be accessed with the permission of the archivist.
CONTAINER LIST
- Binghamton Psychiatric Center, 1973, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Salary list from 1887, History Pamphlets, Journal Article, Transcript of tapes 2-6 (Box 6)
- Binghamton Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Correspondence, Transcript of Tapes 9-10 (Box 4)
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Synopses, Transcript
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Synopsis, Correspondence, Transcript of Tape 6 (Box 3)
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Two checks, Synopsis, Consent and Release form, Transcript of Tape 5 (Box 3)
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Correspondence, Transcript of Tapes 11-12 (Box 3)
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Synopsis, Correspondence, Consent and Release Form, Transcript of Tape 1 (Box 4)
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Synopsis, Consent and Release form and check, Transcript of Tape tape 4 (Box 3)
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Synopses, Transcripts of Tapes 5-6 (Box 4), Consent and Release Forms, Correspondence
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Correspondence, Synopsis, Transcript of Tapes 2-4 (Box 4)
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Synopsis, Consent and Release Forms and checks, Correspondence, Transcript of Tapes 9-10 (Box 3)
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Synopsis, Consent and Release Forms and Checks, Correspondence, Transcript of Tapes 7-8 (Box 3)
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Synopsis, Consent and Release Forms and Checks, Correspondence, Previous Work Experience, Transcript of Tape 13 (Box 3)
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Synopsis, Consent and Release Forms and Checks, Correspondence, Transcript of Tape 1 (Box 3)
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Consent and Release Forms and Checks, Correspondence, Transcript of Tapes 2-3 (Box 3)
- Gowanda State Hospital, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Synopsis, Correspondence, Transcript of Tapes 7-8 (Box 4)
- Pilgrim State Hospital, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Correspondence, Work History, Articles, Bibliography Transcript of Tapes 11-13 (Box 4)
- Rochester Psychiatric Center, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Transcript of Tapes 3-5 (Box 9)
- Rochester Psychiatric Center, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Transcript of Tapes 5-6 (Box 9)
- Rochester Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Transcript of Tapes 6-7 (Box 9)
- Rochester Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Transcript of Tapes 12-14 (Box 10)
- Rochester Psychiatric Center, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Transcript of Tapes 8-9 (Box 10)
- Rochester Psychiatric Center, 1983, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 23, 25)
  Correspondence, Transcript of Tapes 7-8 (Box 10), Articles
- Rochester Psychiatric Center, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Transcript of Tapes 10-12 (Box 9)
- Rochester Psychiatric Center, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Transcript of tapes 7-9 (Box 9)
- Rockland Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Newspaper Article, Transcript of Tapes 6-7 (Box 8)
- St. Lawrence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Floppy Disk, Transcript of tapes 4-5(Box 10)
- St. Lawrence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Transcript of Tapes 9-11 (Box 7)
- St. Lawrence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Transcript of tapes 14-15 (Box 7)
- St. Lawrence Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Transcript of Tapes 15 (Box 7) and 1 (Box 10)
- St. Lawrence Psychiatric Center, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Transcript of Tapes 11-12 (Box 7)
- St. Lawrence Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Transcript of Tapes 13 (Box 7)
- St. Lawrence Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Transcript of Tapes 7-8 (Box 7)
- St. Lawrence Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Transcript of Tapes 2-3 (Box 10)
- Sunmount Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Transcript of Tapes 12-14 (Box 8)
- Willard Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  Transcript of Tapes 10-11 (Box 10)
- Willard Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  Transcript of Tapes 13-14 (Box 5)
- Willard Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  Transcript of Tapes 5-7 (Box 5)
- Willard Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  Transcript of Tapes 3-4 (Box 5)
- Willard Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  Transcript of Tape 10 (Box 5)
- Willard Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  Transcript of Tapes 15-16 (Box 5)
- Willard Psychiatric Center, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  Transcript of Tapes 11-12 (Box 5)
- Department of Mental Hygiene, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Transcript of Tape 1 (Box 8)
- Department of Mental Hygiene, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  Correspondence, Articles, Transcript of Tapes 11-12 (Box 7)
- New York State Psychiatric Institute, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  Transcript of Tape 3 (Box 8)
- Transcript, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  Transcript of Tape 1 (Box 6)
- Transcript, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  Transcript of Tapes 1-2 (Box 8)
- Book Correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Articles, Correspondence
- History of Willard Asylum for the Insane and the Willard State Hospital, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Bibliography, 1981, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  Articles
- Bibliography, 1954-1955, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  Articles: History of the Department of Mental Hygiene, State Hospitals for the Mentally Ill
- Bibliography, 1981,1991, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  Articles on Mental Health, Questionnaire, Notes
- Bibliography, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  Newspaper Articles pertaining to mental health
- Bibliography-Willard Asylum for the Insane, 1982, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  Newspaper Articles
- Bibliography, 1981, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  Book Search Records, Articles
- Bibliography, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  Miscellaneous articles
- Statistics, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  Correspondence, Various Hospital Patient and Staff Statistics
- Albert Deutsch "The Mentally Ill in america", 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Interview Question Cards (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Notebooks, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  Annual Reports and Outline,Various Hospitals
- Willard State Hospital Annual Reports, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Working Book Draft, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  CD copies, Printed Draft
- Handbook of the Department and State Hospitals, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Willard State Hospital Annual Records (Book), 1916-1931 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Pictorial Album of the Willard Asylum, 1869-1886, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Laws Relating to Willard Asylum for the Insane and Rules and Regulations of Said Asylum, 1870-1881 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Hospital and Community Psychiatry, 1976,1981 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
- Charles Mercer "Lunatic Asylums: Their Organisation and Management", 1894 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Twenty-Seventh Annual Report of the Trustees of Willard State Hospital (Book), 1895 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Interview Tapes, 1983-1984 (Box 3-10)
  Alphabetic listing of names of interviewees is available offline. Patrons may request confirmation of inclusion of individuals from staff.
  - Gowanda, September 1983 (Box 3)
  - Gowanda, October 1983 (Box 4)
  - Willowbrook, April, June 1984 (Box 5)
  - Binghamptom, Pilgrim, October - November 1983 (Box 6)
  - Pilgrim, St. Lawrence, November - December 1983 (Box 7)
  - Albany, Rockland, Sunmount, September 1983, April 1984 (Box 8)
  - Rochester, Willowbrook, April, June 1984 (Box 9)
  - Rochester, St. Lawrence, December 1983, January 1984 (Box 10)
- Interview Tape Copies, 1983-1984 (Box 11-15)